<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sad news from Salisbury, and other parts of the west of England. Being an account of a most sad and dreadful frost and snow, which hapned on the 23d. of December 1684. in and about most parts of the west of England, which froze to death many poor passengers who travelled the rode, besides many beasts, incredible to believe, but that some who were in the same storm are alive to justify the truth thereof ... To the tune of, Aim not too high.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S255A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183157</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47012631</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47012631</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174596</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174596)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2692:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sad news from Salisbury, and other parts of the west of England. Being an account of a most sad and dreadful frost and snow, which hapned on the 23d. of December 1684. in and about most parts of the west of England, which froze to death many poor passengers who travelled the rode, besides many beasts, incredible to believe, but that some who were in the same storm are alive to justify the truth thereof ... To the tune of, Aim not too high.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for P. Brooksby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication taken from Wing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Contains 3 illustrations.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Glasgow. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:174596:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <head>Sad News from Salisbury, And other Parts of the Weſt of ENGLAND.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Being an Account of a moſt ſad and Dreadful Froſt and Snow, which hapned on the 23d. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1684. in and about moſt Parts of the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> which Froze to Death many poor paſſengers who Travelled the Rode, beſides many Beaſts, Incredible to believe, but that ſome who were in the ſame Storm are alive to juſtifie the truth thereof, the like ſcarce ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing known in this Kingdom.</p>
            </argument>
            <opener>To the Tune of, <hi>Aim not too High.</hi>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>GOod Chriſtians all that live both far &amp; near,</l>
               <l>A ſad and dreadful ſtory you ſhall hear,</l>
               <l>Which I do hope will warning be to all,</l>
               <l>Leaſt greater Iudgments on this land befall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>pon the three and twentieth of <hi>December</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A day which ſome have reaſon to remember,</l>
               <l>A dreadful ſtorm did happen in the <hi>Weſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe ſad effects ſhall chiefly be expreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As Paſſengers along the Rode did go</l>
               <l>The <hi>North-eaſt</hi> wind moſt bitterly did blow,</l>
               <l>And flakes of <hi>Snow</hi> did from the Heavens fall,</l>
               <l>As if it meant deſtruction unto all,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Carryers that the rode full well did know,</l>
               <l>Did looſe their way, by reaſon of the <hi>Snow,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Many were forced to refine their breath,</l>
               <l>And in this tempeſt frozen were to death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Collins</hi> the <hi>Taunton</hi> Carryer, people ſay,</l>
               <l>Vpon the <hi>Douns</hi> did ſtrangly looſe his way,</l>
               <l>Two of his Paſſengers were ſtarv'd with cold,</l>
               <l>A fearful Spectacle for to behold.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>And <hi>Mathews</hi> that belong'd to <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did bare a part in this extremity,</l>
               <l>Two Horſes dy'd, and by the <hi>Snow</hi> and <hi>Froſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some ſay the uſe of both his hands are loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Two Paſſingers that were both Man and wife</l>
               <l>In this extremity did part with life,</l>
               <l>It would have griev'd a ſtony heart to ſee't,</l>
               <l>How theſe poor ſouls lay ſtarved feet to feet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And this for truth report us plainly tells,</l>
               <l>The Carryer that belong'd to <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His own dear Son was frozen unto death;</l>
               <l>And on the <hi>Douns</hi> did looſe his dea reſt breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The father griev'd to ſee his ſon ſo loſt,</l>
               <l>By reaſon of this ſharp and cuel Froſt,</l>
               <l>It was a great affliction to his mind,</l>
               <l>Yet forced was to leave his corps behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Lady <hi>Fines</hi> that at <hi>New-Tony</hi> dwelt,</l>
               <l>One of her Servants this cold ſeaſon felt,</l>
               <l>He froze to death was driving of his Cart,</l>
               <l>Which pierc'd his tender Lrdy to the heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A <hi>Shop-keeper</hi> that did to Market go,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Salisbury,</hi> was like wiſe loſt alſo,</l>
               <l>With many more which here I ſhall omit,</l>
               <l>Yet this ſad time I never ſhall forget,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thirty more in <hi>Somerſtſhire</hi> were leſt</l>
               <l>In this unuſual <hi>Snow</hi> and cruel Froſt,</l>
               <l>Who little thought when they went out of door,</l>
               <l>Their wives &amp; children they ſhould ſee no more,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Near <hi>Tiverton in Devonſhire</hi> they ſay,</l>
               <l>As many to the Markets took their way,</l>
               <l>Were in this Tempeſt loſt, and ne'r were found,</l>
               <l>Till at the laſt found ſtarved on the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This judgment came from gods almighty hand</l>
               <l>For ſins committed in our native land,</l>
               <l>Lord grant that it to us a warning be</l>
               <l>And teach us how to ſhun iniquitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our ſins for vengeance do to Heaven cry,</l>
               <l>Yet we like ſinners live in vanity,</l>
               <l>O grant that we our ſinful lives may mend,</l>
               <l>That we may live with thee when life doth end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From ſtorms &amp; tempeſts Lord preſerve u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtill,</l>
               <l>Teach us thy holy laws for to fulfill,</l>
               <l>So ſhall we gainers be by looſing breath,</l>
               <l>And ride triumphant o're the ſecond death.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="account_of_survivors">
            <p>For the better ſatisfaction of the Incredulous, I here inſert the Names of ſeveral who have ſufficiently taſted of the bitterneſs of this outragious Storm and Froſt, and are yet alive to teſtifie the Verity thereof.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Mathews</hi> the Carrier of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> who had ſeveral of his Cattle dyed, and he himſelf loſt the uſe of both his hands: Mr. <hi>Morris</hi> and Mr. <hi>Clark,</hi> Carriers to <hi>Exeter</hi> and <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> were much endangered of their lives: the Carrier to <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> had one paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger froze to death beſides his own Son, a man and his Wife going with the <hi>Taunton</hi> Carrier, were both froze to death, and found dead foot to foot, with about 30 more near <hi>Evill</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire;</hi> and 6 or 7 near <hi>Chard,</hi> and many more, beſides ſome ſtore of Horſes and Oxen, too many to be here inſerted.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>P.</hi> Brooksby, at the Golden Ball in Pyecorner.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
